<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from France. Or A relation of a maruellous and fearfull accident of a disaster which happened at Paris the seuenth day of March, this present yeare 1618. where by meanes of a terrible fire, all the pallace was burnt and consumed. Together with a narration of the losse and ruine of many tradesmen, who had all their goods consumed by the said fire. As also an iniunction of the Court of Parliament concerning the restoring backe and deliuering of all bags of papers, processes, peeces and records which were taken vp being cast out of the pallace during the said fire. / Truly translated according to the French copie: and set forth by authoritie..</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01167</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11281</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121558</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856737</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856737</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22361</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01167)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22361)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1172:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from France. Or A relation of a maruellous and fearfull accident of a disaster which happened at Paris the seuenth day of March, this present yeare 1618. where by meanes of a terrible fire, all the pallace was burnt and consumed. Together with a narration of the losse and ruine of many tradesmen, who had all their goods consumed by the said fire. As also an iniunction of the Court of Parliament concerning the restoring backe and deliuering of all bags of papers, processes, peeces and records which were taken vp being cast out of the pallace during the said fire. / Truly translated according to the French copie: and set forth by authoritie..</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by William Iones, for Nathaniell Browne, and are to be solde, at the next shoppe to the great north doore of saint Paules Church.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B²  (-A1, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fires --  France --  Paris --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Palais de Justice de Paris --  Fire, 1618] --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Parlement --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Paris (France) --  History --  Louis XIII, 1610-1643 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22361:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:22361:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <p>Newes from France.</p>
            <p>OR A relation of a maruellous and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full accident of a diſaſter, which happened at PARIS the ſeuenth day of March, this preſent yeare 1618. where by meanes of a terrible fire, all the Pallace was burnt and conſumed.</p>
            <p>Together with a narration of the loſſe and ruine of many Tradeſmen, who had all their goods conſumed by the ſaid fire.</p>
            <p>As alſo an Iniunction of the Court of Parliament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the reſtoring backe and deliuering of all bags of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Proceſſes, peeces and Records which were taken vp being caſt out of the Pallace during the ſaid fire.</p>
            <p>Truly tranſlated according to the French Copie: and ſet forth by authoritie.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Iones,</hi> for <hi>Nathaniell Browne,</hi> and are to be ſolde, at the next ſhoppe to the great North <hi>doore of ſaint</hi> Paules <hi>Church.</hi> 1618.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:22361:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:22361:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <head>NEWES FROM <hi>France.</hi> Or a Relation of the maruelous <hi>and fearfeull accident of a diſaſter, which happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> at <hi>Paris</hi> the ſeuenth day of <hi>March this preſent yeare.</hi> 1618. <hi>Where by</hi> meanes of a terrible fire all the <hi>Palace was burnt and conſumed.</hi> TOGETHER WITH A NARRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the loſſe and ruine of many tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>who had all their goods conſumed</hi> by the ſaid fier. <hi>AS ALSO AN INIVNCTION OF THE</hi> Court of Parliament concerning the <hi>reſtoring and deleuiring backe of all</hi> bagges of papers &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthie Reader, the Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thour being curious to giue you to vnderſtand a matter prodigious and feaerfull, which is altogeather wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of memorie, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marked of many men of qualitie as well ſpirituall as temporall ſeeing an accident to happen in the beſt peece of the famous Citie of <hi>Paris,</hi> being a
<pb facs="tcp:22361:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->place where true and vpright iuſtice ought without delay to be done, named the <hi>Palace</hi> of the Kinges of <hi>France</hi> and the moſt renowned in the world by Reaſon of a Chappell named the Holie, the which Almightie God hath preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the gulfe of an horrible &amp; vnquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fier, which deſcended from Heauen, about midnight in the forme and faſhion of a terrible great flaming ſtarre, being for the bignes one cubite in length and of one foote in breadth, the which conſuming fier did burne and waſte the full ſpace of a day and an a halfe within the great Hall of the <hi>Palace</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> without being able to be ſtaied or quenched by any meanes, as ſhewinge that this fier would demonſtrate the Iuſtice of God and the anger and wrath of the moſte holie <hi>Trinitie</hi> declaring vnto ſinners that they ſhould be conuerted and haue God alwai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before their eyes without muſing and troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge themſelues in heaping vp worldly good; and tranſitorie riches, and leauing the meanes to come to the kingdome of God vnſought for. In ſuch ſort began the fier the ſeuenth day of <hi>March,</hi> about an hower after midnight that with the force thereof it burned and conſumed all the auncient Antiquities and Records of this Realme of <hi>France</hi> hauing made in one night a greater deluge and deſtruction, then a hundred men are able to reſtore and build vp in a yeare.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>But God hath preſerued the Chappell called the Holy ſhewing to his people that he deſires to be honored and glorified.</p>
            <p>We may well know that this fier ſignifieth
<pb facs="tcp:22361:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->vnto vs a beginning of the wrath of God and that he is angry againſt vs, for this fier puts vs in mind of the ende of the world, and ſhould ſtirre vs vp to the firme beliefe which we ought to haue in the ſpirituall merrcy of God, and to hold our ſelues alwaéyes ready to fight againſt the enimie of our ſoules, and to embrace the true God and Sauiour. And namely in this holie time of Lent we ought to reconcile our ſelues vnto God and to demande pardon and mercy of him for all our finnes, that thereby we may come to the hiretage which he hath purchaſed by his death and paſſion, beſeeching him to haue pitty vpon vs, and to preſerue vs henceforth from ſuch accidents.</p>
            <figure/>
         </div>
         <div type="decree">
            <pb facs="tcp:22361:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
            <head>The Arreſt or Decree of the Court of Parliament of PARIS touching <hi>the reſtoring of the papers and</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters which were caſt by <hi>during the ſaid fier.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Court vpon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint made thereunto, by the <hi>Attourney</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the <hi>King</hi> touching the diuerting and caſting aſide of the bagges, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, papers, parchments and regiſters made in the Pallace during the time of the fier hath enioyned and doth enioyne, all perſons of what qualitie eſtate and condition ſoeuer they be, which haue taken or caried away founde by accident or by what meanes ſoeuer there be come into their hands, any of the ſaid bagges proceſſe, peeces, titles, Regeſter minutes and other papers, that they doe ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyly, and readily cary and put them into the hands of Maiſter <hi>Iohn Du Tillet Regeſter</hi> or
<pb facs="tcp:22361:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
               <hi>Greffier</hi> of the ſaid Court, or into the hands of his Deputy in his houſe ſcitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te in the ſtreet <hi>Debu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi</hi> in this Citty of <hi>Paris,</hi> without retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or keeping backe any of them by guile fraud or otherwiſe, vpon paine of exemplary puniſhment. Of which bagges, Regiſters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and letters, the ſaid <hi>Greffier</hi> or his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty ſhall keepe a Regeſter of the names, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names and dwelling places of thoſe which ſhall ſo bring them, for which he ſhall giue them a full diſcharge, that afterwards the ſaid bagges and writtinges may be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the <hi>Pronotares Ciuill</hi> and <hi>Criminill,</hi> to whom the ſame ſhall belong.</p>
            <p>Inhibiting and forbidding vpon the ſame paines all Tradeſmen, Apothecaryes, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of paper, Lardmakers, Mercers, Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers and any others to buy directly or inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly either by themſelues or meanes of any other perſons any Parchments, Papers, writ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en in minute, or in bundles, nor to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them about their packetts and trade: but if any ſhall be brought and offered vnto them they are enioyned to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etaine them, and ſhew them to the Iuſtices &amp; to the end none may pretende cauſe of ignorance this preſent Areſt and Decree ſhall be read and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aſ well by the ſound of the Trumpet and the publicke cry, as alſo by the Prieſts of the Churches of the Pariſhes in the time
<pb facs="tcp:22361:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->of ſeruice, and it is ordained that the <hi>Attour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> generall of the King ſhall haue a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to informe hunſelfe of the retention and concealment, and permitt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h him to giue monition and warning that notice and reuelation may be the better had. Giuen in the Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the eight day of <hi>March 1618.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed Voyſin.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>
               <figure>
                  <q>IN DOMINO CONFIDO</q>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
